Guide to the Robert Fridenberg Collection of Portrait and Topographical Prints
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Portraits, Series I
  - Classical Figures: Historical
    - Valerius Poplicola, Publius (Box 265, Folder 4259)
    - Vespasian, Emperor of Rome, 9-79 (Box 265, Folder 4260)
    - Virgil (Box 265, Folder 4261)
    - Virgil - Scenes from writings (Box 265, Folder 4262)
    - Vitellius, Aulus, Emperor of Rome, 15-69 (Box 265, Folder 4263)
    - Xenophon (Box 265, Folder 4264)
    - Oversize
      - A - Augustus, 17 (Box 266 (Oversize), Folder 4265-4281)
      - Caesar - Virgil, 40 (Box 267 (Oversize), Folder 4282-4321)
  - Classical Figures: Mythological
    These folders contain characters from classical mythologies of Greece and Rome: gods (e.g. Apollo), minor deities and divine beings (e.g., personifications, Sylvans), figures with little or no historical basis (e.g., Romulus), or are figures from literature (e.g., Dido from the Aeneid, scenes from Homer's Iliad, characters from Ovid's Metamorphoses). Characters have their own folders if prints were numerous, or characters were particularly well-known and therefore researchers were likely to look for them. The "miscellaneous" folders contain figures which did not fit easily into any category, including scenes from Greek and Roman life, and depictions of objects that were not busts. Busts that were not obviously identified as any particular figure are grouped together. Use the Oxford Classical Dictionary Online to determine whether characters are mythological or historical.
    - A - Z, 2 (Box 268, Folder 4322-4323)
    - Apollo (Greek deity) (Box 268, Folder 4324)
    - Bacchus (Greek deity) (Box 268, Folder 4325)
    - Busts (Box 268, Folder 4326)
    - Cupid (Roman deity) (Box 268, Folder 4327)
    - Diana (Roman deity)
    - Dido, Queen of Carthage (Box 268, Folder 4328)
    - Hercules (Roman mythology) (Box 268, Folder 4329)
    - Hero and Leander (Greek mythology) (Box 268, Folder 4330)
    - Homer. Iliad (Box 268, Folder 4331)
    - Homer. Odyssey (Box 268, Folder 4332)
    - Jupiter (Roman deity) (Box 268, Folder 4333)
    - Medusa (Greek mythology) (Box 268, Folder 4334)
    - Mercury (Roman deity) (Box 268, Folder 4335)
    - Minerva (Roman deity) (Box 268, Folder 4336)
    - Muses (Greek deities) (Box 268, Folder 4337)
    - Orpheus (Greek mythology)
    - Personifications (Box 268, Folder 4338)
    - Romulus, King of Rome, and Remus (Box 268, Folder 4339)
    - Sylvans (Box 268, Folder 4340)
    - Theseus (Greek mythology) (Box 268, Folder 4341)
    - Virtues (Box 268, Folder 4342)
    - Miscellaneous Greek objects and scenes (Box 268, Folder 4343)
    - Miscellaneous Roman objects and scenes (Box 268, Folder 4344)
    - Oversize
      - A - Miscellaneous Roman, 21 (Box 269 (Oversize), Folder 4345-4365)
- Topographical Views, Series II
  28 boxes are British Isles. largest portion of the series.
  - British Isles
    - England and Wales
      - Cathedrals
        - A - P, 19 (Box 270, Folder 4366-4384)
        - R - Y, 11 (Box 271, Folder 4385-4395)
      - Churches
        - A - E, 9 (Box 272, Folder 4396-4404)
        - F - M, 10 (Box 273, Folder 4405-4414)
        - N - V, 8 (Box 274, Folder 4415-4422)
        - W - Z, 3 (Box 275, Folder 4423-4425)
      - Cities, Towns, and Villages
        - A - Cambridge, 12 (Box 276, Folder 4426-4437)
        - Cambridge - Cumberland, 11 (Box 277, Folder 4438-4448)
        - Dalton - Henley, 10 (Box 278, Folder 4449-4458)
        - Hereford - Lundisfarne, 10 (Box 279, Folder 4459-4468)
        - London
          - Admiralty and Horse Guards (Box 280, Folder 4469)
          - Almshouses (Box 280, Folder 4470)
          - Asylums (Box 280, Folder 4471)
          - Banks (Box 280, Folder 4472)
          - Bridges, 3 (Box 280, Folder 4473-4475)
          - Buckingham Palace (Box 280, Folder 4476)
          - Canals (Box 280, Folder 4477)
          - Clubs and Societies (Box 280, Folder 4480)
          - Docks (Box 280, Folder 4481)
          - Exchanges (Box 280, Folder 4482)
          - Guild Hall (Box 281, Folder 4483)
          - Halls, 2 (Box 281, Folder 4484-4485)
          - Historic Buildings (Box 281, Folder 4486)
          - Hospitals (Box 281, Folder 4487)
          - Hotels (Box 281, Folder 4488)
          - Inns of Chancery (Box 281, Folder 4489)
          - Lambeth Palace (Box 281, Folder 4490)
          - Mansion House (Box 282, Folder 4491)
          - Mansions, 2 (Box 282, Folder 4492-4493)
          - Museums and Galleries (Box 282, Folder 4494)
          - Palaces (general) (Box 282, Folder 4495)
          - Parliament (Box 282, Folder 4496)
          - Schools, 2 (Box 282, Folder 4497-4498)
          - Somerset House (Box 282, Folder 4499)
          - Squares (Box 282, Folder 4500)
          - Streets, 2 (Box 283, Folder 4501-4502)
          - Whitehall (Box 283, Folder 4503)
          - Plates from London Interiors (London: Joseph Mead, 1841-1844), 5 (Box 283, Folder 4504-4508)
            Contains plates removed from the two-volume publication; no text pages are present.
          - Miscellaneous (Box 283, Folder 4509)
        - Maentwrog Bridge - Newcastle, 5 (Box 284, Folder 4510-4514)
        - Newchurch - Petersham, 10 (Box 285, Folder 4515-4524)
        - Pickering - Sopley, 11 (Box 286, Folder 4525-4535)
        - Stanmore - York, 10 (Box 287, Folder 4536-4545)
      - Country Houses and Castles, Most of the houses in this set of folders are filed under the name of the house, but readers should also look under the owner's name. In only a few cases is the house filed under a location, such as Twickenham.
        - A - L, 14 (Box 288, Folder 4546-4559)
        - M - P, 13 (Box 289, Folder 4560-4572)
        - Q - T, 14 (Box 290, Folder 4573-4586)
        - U - Z, 6 (Box 291, Folder 4587-4592)
      - Isle of Man (Box 292, Folder 4593)
      - Isle of Wight (Box 292, Folder 4594)
      - Lakes, Rivers, and Waterfalls, 11 (Box 292, Folder 4595-4605)
      - Maps (Box 292, Folder 4606)
    - Ireland
      - Maps and genre prints (Box 293, Folder 4607)
      - A - D, 9 (Box 293, Folder 4608-4616)
      - E - Z, 10 (Box 294, Folder 4617-4626)
    - Scotland
      Related Materials
      See also Book Illustration - Life of Burns
      - Maps (Box 295, Folder 4627)
      - A - C, 9 (Box 295, Folder 4628-4636)
      - D - K, 11 (Box 296, Folder 4637-4647)
      - L - Z, 10 (Box 297, Folder 4648-4657)
  - France
    - Maps (Box 298, Folder 4658)
    - A - C, 8 (Box 298, Folder 4659-4666)
    - Corsica (Box 298, Folder 4667)
    - D - M, 10 (Box 299, Folder 4668-4677)
    - N - P, 4 (Box 300, Folder 4678-4681)
    - Paris
      - Maps (Box 300, Folder 4682)
      - General views (Box 300, Folder 4683)
      - Arc de Triomphe (Box 300, Folder 4684)
      - Barrieres (Box 300, Folder 4685)
      - Bourse / Exchange (Box 300, Folder 4686)
      - Bridges (Box 300, Folder 4687)
      - Chambers of Deputies and Peers (Box 300, Folder 4688)
      - Churches
        - A - D (Box 301, Folder 4689)
        - Saint. Denis (Box 301, Folder 4690)
        - E (Box 301, Folder 4691)
        - Sainte-Étienne de Mont (Box 301, Folder 4692)
        - F - I (Box 301, Folder 4693)
        - Invalides (Box 301, Folder 4694)
        - J - M (Box 301, Folder 4695)
        - La Madeleine (Box 301, Folder 4696)
        - N - R (Box 301, Folder 4697)
        - Notre Dame de Paris (Box 301, Folder 4698)
        - Panthéon / Sainte-Genevieve (Box 301, Folder 4699)
        - S (Box 301, Folder 4700)
        - T - Z (Box 301, Folder 4701)
      - Fountains and pumps (Box 302, Folder 4702)
      - Gardens, expositions, theaters, cafes (Box 302, Folder 4703)
      - Genre scenes (Box 302, Folder 4704)
      - Hospitals and morgue (Box 302, Folder 4705)
      - Hotels (Box 302, Folder 4706)
      - Hôtel des Invalides (Box 302, Folder 4707)
      - Hôtel de Ville (Box 302, Folder 4708)
      - Markets (Box 302, Folder 4709)
      - Mint (Box 302, Folder 4710)
      - Observatory (Box 302, Folder 4711)
      - Palaces and chateaux (Box 302, Folder 4712)
      - Palace of Justice (Box 303, Folder 4713)
      - Palace of the Legion of Honor (Box 303, Folder 4714)
      - Palace of the Louvre (Box 303, Folder 4715)
      - Palace of the Luxembourg (Box 303, Folder 4716)
      - Palais Royale (Box 303, Folder 4717)
      - Père Lachaise Cemetery (Box 303, Folder 4718)
      - Place A - Z (Box 303, Folder 4719)
      - Place Louis VIII - XVI (Box 303, Folder 4720)
      - Place Vendôme (Box 303, Folder 4721)
      - Portes (Box 303, Folder 4722)
      - Porte Ste. Denis (Box 303, Folder 4723)
      - Prisons (Box 303, Folder 4724)
      - Public buildings (Box 303, Folder 4725)
      - Schools (Box 304, Folder 4726)
      - Seine and canals (Box 304, Folder 4727)
      - Street scenes (Box 304, Folder 4728)
      - Tuileries (Box 304, Folder 4729)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 304, Folder 4730)
    - Q - S, 4 (Box 304, Folder 4731-4734)
    - Saint A - Z (Box 304, Folder 4735)
    - Saint-Cloud (Box 305, Folder 4736)
    - T - V, 5 (Box 305, Folder 4737-4741)
    - Versailles - Eugène Sadoux etchings (Box 305, Folder 4742)
    - W - Z, 2 (Box 305, Folder 4743-4744)
  - Africa, 6 (Box 306, Folder 4745-4750)
  - Australia, New Zealand, and Île Amsterdam (Box 306, Folder 4751)
  - Belgium, 7 (Box 306, Folder 4752-4758)
  - China, 2 (Box 306, Folder 4759-4760)
  - Denmark (Box 306, Folder 4761)
  - Finland (Box 306, Folder 4762)
  - Germany
    - A - D, 6 (Box 307, Folder 4763-4768)
    - E - K, 8 (Box 308, Folder 4769-4776)
    - L - P, 7 (Box 309, Folder 4777-4783)
    - R - Z, 9 (Box 310, Folder 4784-4792)
  - Greece, 14 (Box 311, Folder 4793-4806)
  - India, 2 (Box 312, Folder 4807-4808)
  - Indonesia (Box 312, Folder 4809)
    Contains prints formerly filed under Java, Malay Islands, Papua, and Timor.
  - Italy
    - A - N, 11 (Box 313, Folder 4810-4820)
    - O - R, 5 (Box 314, Folder 4821-4825)
    - Rome
      - General views and plans (Box 314, Folder 4826)
      - Arches (Box 314, Folder 4827)
      - Baths (Box 314, Folder 4828)
      - Bridges and gates (Box 314, Folder 4829)
      - Capitol (Box 314, Folder 4830)
      - Churches (Box 314, Folder 4831)
      - Circus (Box 314, Folder 4832)
      - Coliseum (Box 314, Folder 4833)
      - Forum, 2 (Box 314, Folder 4834-4835)
      - Palaces, castles, and villas (Box 315, Folder 4836)
      - Plazas and monuments (Box 315, Folder 4837)
      - Temples (Box 315, Folder 4838)
      - Tombs (Box 315, Folder 4839)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 315, Folder 4840)
    - S - T, 4 (Box 315, Folder 4841-4844)
    - U - V, 6 (Box 316, Folder 4845-4850)
  - Japan, 2 (Box 317, Folder 4851-4852)
  - Malta (Box 317, Folder 4853)
  - Netherlands (Box 317, Folder 4854)
  - Norway (Box 317, Folder 4855)
  - Peru (Box 317, Folder 4856)
  - Philippines and Guam (Box 317, Folder 4857)
  - Portugal (Box 317, Folder 4858)
  - Russia, 3 (Box 317, Folder 4859-4861)
  - Spain, including Gibraltar and the Balearic Islands, 7 (Box 318, Folder 4862-4868)
  - Sri Lanka (Box 318, Folder 4869)
  - Sweden (Box 318, Folder 4870)
  - Switzerland, 11 (Box 319, Folder 4871-4881)
  - United States
    - A - Z, 23 (Box 321, Folder 4891-4913)
    - Plates from Rae's Philadelphia Pictorial Directory and Panoramic Advertiser (Philadelphia: Julio H. Rae, 1851), 3 (Box 322 (Oversize), Folder 4914-4916)
- Book Illustrations
  - Addison, Joseph
  - Aesop's Fables, 1793
  - Ainsworth, William Harrison - Old St. Paul's, 1841
  - Arabian Nights Entertainment, 1785
  - Bunyan, John - Pilgrim's Progress, 1838
    - Burns, Robert - miscellaneous
  - Cooke's Select British Novels, 1838
  - Cooke's Select British Poets
  - Cooke's Sacred Classics, 1838
  - Cooke's Select British Poets, 1800
  - Browne, Hablot Knight - The Chronicles of Crime, edited by Camden Pelham Esq.
  - Byron, George Gordon Byron, Baron - Life of Byron
  - Cooper, James Fenimore, 6
    Includes plates from Le Bravo,
  - Cooper, James Fenimore - Homeward Bound
  - Cooper, James Fenimore - Last of the Mohicans
  - Cooper, James Fenimore - Lionel Lincoln
  - Cooper, James Fenimore - The Spy
  - Cooper, James Fenimore - miscellaneous
  - Defoe, Daniel - The Life and Adventures of Robinson Crusoe, 1781-1790
  - Falconer, William - The Shipwreck, 1795-1825
  - Smollet, Tobias
  - Wilson, John - The Land of Burns, 1841
- Other Prints, Series IV
  - American Civil War
    A small group of prints, photographs, and printed material related to the American Civil War, Abraham Lincoln, and various military officers and associates of Lincoln. There are no original photographs of Lincoln in the collection.
    - Abraham Lincoln
    - Civil War officers and Lincoln associates
    - Civil War officers
    - Mathew B. Brady photograph: Headquarters, Army of the Cumberland, Chattanooga, Tennessee, 1860-1865
    - Battle scenes in chronological order
    - Other scenes
  - Engravers and lithographers
    The folders contain prints, largely portraits, filed by the name of the engraver or lithographer, arranged as received with the collection in 1999. It is not known if the prints were grouped before or after arriving at Yale.
    - Banknote engravings
      One folder of small portraits of men engraved specifically for bank notes, stock certificates, and other financial or legal documents. Most are unattributed as to engraver or subject; some are credited to the American Bank Note Company, the Continental Basnk Note Company, and the New York Bank Note Company, among others.
    - Bacle, César Hipólito, 1794-1838
    - Cheney, John, 1801-1885
    - Edwin, David, 1776-1841 -- 2 folders
    - Gimbrede, Thomas, 1781-1832
    - Haines, William, 1778-1848
    - Leney, William Satchwell, 1769-1831
    - Longacre, James Barton, 1794-1869
    - Scoles, John, 1772?-1853
    - Rollinson, William, 1762-1842
    - Miscellaneous
      Holds single examples by engravers such as Gideon Fairman, Benjamin Tanner, and others.
  - Miscellaneous
    - Historic Trees
- Robert Fridenberg Archival Material, 1873-1945; Series V; 3.4
  The series holds material related to the business and shop of Robert Fridenberg, including one folder of correspondence, folders of want lists, notes, and other lists, and examples of folders in which the shop housed prints. The single folder of letters contains inquiries from dealers, patrons, and engravers who did business with James Osborne Wright and Robert Fridenberg between 1893 and 1945, and include request lists from people seeking to extra-illustrate specific volumes.
  There is no evidence of the condition and housing of the prints when the collection arrived at Yale University Library with the exception of the oversize prints and some of the topographical prints. The former arrived enclosed in "folders" made from text sheets of folio volumes that had been broken and the plates removed and trimmed, specifically the nine-volume set Galeries historiques du palais de Versailles (Paris: Imprimerie Royale, 1839-1853). Most of the topographical prints remained inside paper folders (many cut down from the Versailles volumes) which were then placed inside the covers of books which had also been broken and the plates removed for sale; Fridenberg retitled the spines with paper labels describing the prints held within, and these "folders," which could stand up on a shelf as a would a book, somewhat protected the merchandise from the layer of black soot that likely eminated from the shop's heating system. Among those brokene sets were Aristide Guilbert's Histoire des Villes de France (Paris: Furne et Cie., 1845-48) and Evert A. Duyckinck's Portrait Gallery of Eminent Men and Women of Europe and America (New York: Johnson, Wilson, 1873). Examples of these and other hollowed-out book covers were kept with the collection for historical purposes.
  - Correspondence, 1893-1945
  - Notes on Washington portraits, undated
  - Want lists, lists, notes, and indexes, 1876-1905
  - Folders formerly housing prints
  - Book covers formerly holding prints
    The boxes hold several examples of the housing Fridenberg employed for storing his topographical prints on bookshelves in his shop.